<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Steam | Byron S. McMullen]]></title>
  <link href="http://Krustal.github.io/blog/categories/steam/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://Krustal.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-29T22:09:48-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://Krustal.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Byron McMullen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Steam Summer Sale 2013 - Post Mortem - 25%]]></title>
    <link href="http://Krustal.github.io/blog/2013/07/31/steam-summer-sale-2013-post-mortem-25-percent/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-31T18:04:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://Krustal.github.io/blog/2013/07/31/steam-summer-sale-2013-post-mortem-25-percent</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>tl;dr</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m figuring out how much money was a complete waste for the last Steam summer sale. These are the first 25%ish of the titles I purchased.</p>

<ul>
<li>Worms Revolution &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Interested</li>
<li>The Cave &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Interested</li>
<li>Fallen Enchantress: Legendary Heroes &ndash; Worthwile &ndash; Excited</li>
<li>Dragon&rsquo;s Lair &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Educational</li>
<li>Gemini Rue &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Interested</li>
<li>Prison Architect &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Excited</li>
<li>Evoland &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Excited</li>
<li>Van Helsing &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Someday</li>
<li>The Swapper &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Excited</li>
<li>Final Fantasy VII &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Someday</li>
<li>Awesomenauts &ndash; Waste &ndash; Unlikely</li>
<li>Poker Night 2 &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Someday</li>
<li>Hotline Miami &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Interested</li>
</ul>


<h2>Explanation</h2>

<p>With this most recent Steam summer sale I bought what I measured to be about 47 new games, DLC, or software titles. Many of these titles were on sale for less that $5 which makes it easy in the moment to justify the purchase of just about anything I have even been remotely interested in. So I have resolved to play each game for a maximum of 1hr and determine if the game was a worthwhile purchase or if I made a rash decision that likely won’t be enjoyable.</p>

<p>Overall there is a boolean decision for any title. Was it worthwhile or a waste. Within those two options there are varying degrees of interest. For worthwhile there are:</p>

<p>Excited, a game that I genuinely look forward to playing through and exploring in the near future.</p>

<p>Interest, a title that doesn’t have the sheer grip of excitement but is intriguing and I hope to play soon. Usually these are titles that are well made and have some interesting mechanic that I don’t understand enough to get really truly excited about in the brief time I spend with the game.</p>

<p>Someday, This is probably the lowest level of worthwhile. A someday title has some element that interests me but overall just doesn’t have the immediate grab that will guarantee I will play it to completion. These are the titles I historically have not purchased myself and asked for during Christmas for birthdays and I have the hardest time finishing.</p>

<p>Education, a classification that lacks a level of interest definition. These are titles that I am glad I purchased but the level of which I enjoy them isn’t typically very important. These are usually classic titles that I have heard a lot about or that explore some really innovative mechanic or technique that I want to witness. I purchased these titles more as a study of game design than as a entertainment title and as such I don’t expect them to necessarily be entertaining, though I always hope.</p>

<h3>Worms Revolution &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Interested</h3>

<p>Like most worms game the singleplayer is not where the fun is. The goofy ridiculous combat become substantially more entertaining when it’s your friend that pulls off that crazy grenade lob across half the level and the not the computationally accurate AI. This is even more the case when the AI seems to be capable of pulling off maneuvers that border on the absurd. Shooting bazooka’s that arc over the entire level before neatly blowing your worm into the water, using just the wind and murderously precise aim. Of course turn based games are a bit of a difficult propositions especially remotely when so much of their appeal stems from being there to live through the miraculous maneuvers and pride destroying slip ups. Skype just doesn’t carry the same weight.</p>

<p><strong>Final verdict:</strong> Worms Revolution is an excellent entry in the worms franchise. It doesn’t really bring anything new that really changes the game so if you already own a worms title buying another one will likely just decrease the odds that a group of friends all have the correct versions. I enjoy the game and hopefully I can get some co workers onboard, otherwise I may trudge through the singleplayer eventually. A worthwhile purchase, just barely.</p>

<h3>The Cave &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Interested</h3>

<p>I will at least be curious to replay this game partly to see how things change.  The simple puzzle and platforming is enjoyable and the visuals make it fun to explore. Perhaps the most interesting element of The Cave is the feel. It’s a cartoonish style with a fair amount of humor and wimsy but the underwriting theme is exceedingly dark. In the short time I spent with it I had already had to do some questionable things in order to progress.  There is a sort of brutal introspection here that questions the ingrained motivation of all games for near constant progression, that anything that progresses your characters interests in inherently a good thing.</p>

<p><strong>Final Verdict</strong>: A worthwhile purchase for it’s mystery and my desire to see each character&rsquo;s backstory. Though I am painfully aware of the fact there are 7 characters and you can only take 3 with you, meaning at least 3 playthroughs with significant repetition.</p>

<h3>Fallen Enchantress: Legendary Heroes &ndash; Worthwile &ndash; Excited</h3>

<p>Very cool, feels very much like a Hoeroes of Might and Magic title with a bit more strategic depth and a little closer to the 4X franchise. Since HMM has been declining over the past few iterations this hopefully can be a worthy successor.</p>

<h3>Dragon’s Lair &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Educational</h3>

<p>Only took me about half an hour to beat but that’s probably only because I didn’t have to pay to play. I’m glad I did play it, you hear so much about some of these old arcade games it’s nice ot actually play one of the more famous ones. I can definitely see how this game was popular back in the day of 8bit graphics.  Also the arcade level of difficulty is a very strange culture shock.</p>

<h3>Gemini Rue &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Interested</h3>

<p>Feels like a true classic adventure game with a little bit of modern design and technology to give it a crisp edge. I’ll be interested to play this to completion later. Definitely seems like the kind of game I might need to start over though to remember what was going on, depending on how long it is until I do play it.</p>

<h3>Prison Architect &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Excited</h3>

<p>The game definitely has a few bugs, though for the most part they seem to be pathing and AI prioritization issues. Mainly things like completing jobs that prevent them from completing later jobs.There is also the indication there will be something like a “story,” which will be interesting. Regardless a quality well thought out sim game has been sorely lacking in modern memory.</p>

<h3>Evoland &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Excited</h3>

<p>The tangibility of the awards in the game makes it one of the most enjoyable to play adventure titles in recent memory.  My guess is I am pretty close to the end of the game after an hour but I could be way off. I’m basing that mainly off the trailer content.</p>

<h3>Van Helsing &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Someday</h3>

<p>It is a solid seeming hack n’ slash dungeon crawler but the level of complexity to the systems and the minimalist storyline means it is a game I will want to put a bit more time into getting started. This style of hook, where the designer almost completely ignores setting up the story to get the player into things immediately typically doesn’t mean a great hook for my through the game. It actually reminds me of the Castelvania: Lords of Shadow title, the gameplay is interesting if nothing completely innovative, but the story never seems to pick up speed. It seems to rely more on the logistical lore of the world than worry about creating any sort of character development.</p>

<h3>The Swapper &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Excited</h3>

<p>A sweeping example of many of the principles of good game design. Game mechanics are simple yet offer a rich set of options that keep the puzzles fresh and challenges while never seeming too impossible. It has a lot of similarities with the Portal franchise, a single mechanic that is used in interesting ways. Games like these seem to lead to solid play; a large part of that is likely the amount of exploration the designers need to make into the mechanic in order to develop interesting puzzles. If they understand the limitations of the mechanic they are more likely to design levels that are well thought out. My one complaint in the time I played was that the game doesn’t properly introduce the fact that creating clones slows time. This is a key mechanic that I didn’t figure out for awhile and left me stumped for a good portion of time. That coupled with the apparent branching level structure left me thinking I had missed something and so I spent a fair amount of time running back and forth trying to figure out what that was and feeling stupid.  The art style was the icing on the cake however as the clay and small object aesthetic completed the immersive aspect of feeling stranded and small.</p>

<h3>Final Fantasy VII &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Someday</h3>

<p>This is a kind of interesting purchase. I’ve played through the majority of FF VII in the past but I’ve never beaten it. I remember it being a really intersting game that was fun to play but like most of the Final Fantasy titles it is extrodinarily long with a fair amount of wandering in the story. I would love to play it to completion some day but the chances of that happening in the enar future seem pretty low as there are lots of other games I want to play. Hopefully someday, but not for awhile.</p>

<h3>Awesomenauts &ndash; Waste &ndash; Unlikely</h3>

<p>Awesomenauts seems like it could be a decent amount of fun. It si the standard Moba formula but in a simpler package that could be more fun for a person like me who doesn’t enjoy the extremely long games that are typically played for other MOBAs.  Unfortunately like most repetitive multiplayer games I will likely never be interested enough without a group of friends who I play with and most of them either aren’t interested or will revert back to DOTA as this isn’t the challenge they are looking for. However, the short games may mean the occasional quick game for me, since it seems likely a relatively easy title to pick back up.</p>

<h3>Poker Night 2 &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Someday</h3>

<p>Poker Night if I look at just the core game mechanics is just a poker game like any other one you might play as part of Windows included game pack. Games like hearts, solitaire, and minecraft. What makes poker night a unique and enjoyable experience is the simulation of a real poker game with friends. You’re constantly trying to listen to what the other players are saying (granted this may whittle down after enough playthroughs) while also strategizing and trying to read your opponents. The real determining factor, and something that is hard to determine in an hour of time with the game is how often things repeat. All the character and appeal of the game is pretty heavily determined by how interesting the character interaction is.</p>

<h3>Hotline Miami &ndash; Worthwhile &ndash; Interested</h3>

<p>So this is the game I show people if I wanted to make sure they hate the idea of video games. it is everything the ignorant populace thinks games are and it is pretty damn fun. It’s a reactive top down shooter along the lines of the original GTAs and more violent.  Almost everything about this game is awful but it is remarkably rewarding and despite all the violence it is probably more of a puzzle game than a shooter. You die in one hit so each encounter needs to be planned out, not just a murder slog. It’s juicy and rewarding and I feel like a horrible person enjoying it but it is rewarding. It also seems to ramp up pretty quickly as difficulty is its main hook and it can get away with that since it is marketing to a hardcore audience or at least an audience that appreciates the raw gameplay of older games.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
